How's it going everyone and welcome back
to another video. In this video, we will
be talking about candle 3 closure. Now,
within my fractal model, there is a
candle 2 and a candle 3 closure. If you
haven't already seen my candle 2 closure
video, please check the link in the
description below to check that out. But
with that said, let's get into the PDF
and learn about candle 3 closure. Now,
the first thing you have to understand
is the difference between a continuation
closure and a reversal closure. When we
have a previous candle's high or low
marked out, if price takes out that low,
for example, and closes below it, that
is a continuation closure. I'm expecting
the next candle to continue lower with
the given trend. Now, with a reversal
closure, that is when price sweeps out
the previous candle's high or low,
closes back above it. So you can see
here price sweeps out the low closes
above it. I'm expecting price to reverse
with the reversal candle and trade back
higher. So that is the reversal closure.
So you need to know the difference
between a continuation closure and a
reversal closure. Now what is the
difference between a candle 2 closure
and a candle 3 closure? In a candle 2
closure, price reversed in candle 2. So
then I could look to trade candle 3 and
candle 4. But if you see here, we hit a
key level but price does not have a
reversal closure. But I cannot expect
price to reverse yet. So here I'm either
looking for price to sweep out its
previous candle's low here to form a
candle 2 closure and then trade higher
or to sweep out its previous high, form
a candle 2 closure and trade lower. Or
we can get a candle 3 closure which is
where price does not sweep out the high
or the low but then closes over the body
of candle 2. You can see here it leaves
the low but closes over the body
engulfing this candle. This is where I
can then expect candle 4 to continue
higher. In this bearish scenario, you
can see we do not get a candle 2
closure. It closes over the high of
candle 1, but candle 3 does not take out
the high of candle 2, but closes below
the body of candle 2. So, engulfing it,
I can then expect candle 4 to trade
lower. So, as we let that play out, you
can see this is where we get our
expansion candle in candle 4 or that
continuation. Now, what I do is I pair
equilibrium with this. So if we have a
nice expansion candle, I'll use the
whole candle's range, the upper half of
that. And that is where I want to see
the wick of candle 4 form if we are
going to expand higher. And in the
bearish scenario, I'll mark out the
entire range of candle 3, looking for
the lower half for candle 4 to continue
lower. But now that you understand the
difference between a candle 2 and a
candle 3 closure, let's get into trading
view and go over a few examples of this.
So here we are on our first example on
EuroUSD daily chart. And if you notice
here, we have a fair value gap. And then
what do we have when price reaches into
this area? We have price sweep out its
previous candle and close back in. So
this is an example of a candle 2 closure
because price takes out its previous
candle, closes back inside as a reversal
closure, and then we get this expansion
here. Now, let's take a look at this one
right here. We sweep out the previous
candle, we close back inside, and we
trade lower. Now, if we're going to
continue this bullish trend, we have a
fair value gap right here. What do we
notice? Price reaches into it, does it
have a reversal closure? No. But that
means it's not a candle to closure. And
I can't just anticipate price to expand
right away in the next candle. I need to
gather some more information. So, with
this, I have two expectations. I'm
either looking for price to sweep out
its previous low and then form a candle
2 closure and I can trade the following
day or we're going to get a candle three
closure in which price is going to close
over the body of candle 2. And here you
can see price does close over the body
of candle 2. So it is a candle 3 closure
and I can anticipate price to trade
higher in the following candle. And
there you can see we get a move higher
in this following candle. So here we are
on our next example on the 4hour INQ
chart. You can see we have taken out
this swing low here. But do we have a
reversal candle? No, we do not cuz price
did not close back inside its previous
candle. So, this is where I need more
information. I'm going to let another
candle print.
And here you can see we do go and close
over the body of candle 2. So, it's
reasonable to say that we have formed a
reversal here. And I could be looking
for price to trade higher. Now, where am
I looking for price to trade higher
from? I'm going to mark out the entire
range of this candle three. And I'd be
looking for this upper half for price to
trade higher in the following candle.
And there you can see we respect the EQ
and we go and trade higher. We're
closing over the previous candle's high.
So, we could expect further
continuation. So, just to review, what
do we have? When we have a point of
interest where we are looking for a
reversal, but we do not have a candle 2
closure, we need to let another candle
print to see if we get a candle 3
closure. Similar to over here, we have
price reaching above this high into a
fair value gap. Do we have a candle 2
closure right here? No, we are closing
over the previous candle's high. But on
the next candle, we don't take out the
previous high, but we do close below the
body of candle 2, giving a candle 3
closure where we can then expect a
continuation lower. And the same thing
here where we have taken out this new
week opening gap. Do we have a candle 2
closure? No, we have a nice wick but no
candle 2 closure. What does the
following candle do? It closes over the
previous candle's body or candle 2's
body and then we get a continuation
higher into these highs. Now, let's take
a look at a few of these swing highs and
lows. You can see we have marked out a
few swing highs and lows. Now, which one
of these are actually valid? Well, this
first one, we do not close back inside
the previous candle's high. So, do we
close below the body of candle 2? No, we
do not. So this is a swing point in
which I will not be focused on because
it is neither a candle 2 or a candle 3
closure. So I go ahead and remove that
from the chart. Now if we take a look
here, do we have a point of interest?
Well, we are just missing this fair
value gap. So although it is a valid
candle to closure, an ideal one, it is
not valid because it is missing that
point of interest. So I'll go ahead and
remove that one as well. Is this one
valid? Yes, it is. as it is reaching
into a fair value gap and closing back
below. Now, although it is mechanically
valid, does it make sense to leave this
high right here? So close? Probably not.
So, I would remove that one as well. So,
as you can see, if we do not have a
point of interest or a valid closure,
I'm not just going to choose random
swing points. I need both of those. You
can see here, this is both a swing high
and a swing low. But is this a valid
one? Well, in the bearish sense, yes, it
is a candle to closure, but we already
reach into these equal lows. So, I
wouldn't really be interested in this or
trading away from these failure swings.
But here you can see we reach into this
point of interest, these equal lows into
the gap. And what do we have? Do we have
a candle 2 closure? No, we do not as we
do not close back inside the previous.
So, then we need to wait for another
candle. After this next candle, what do
we have? We have price closing over the
body of candle 2. So that is a candle
three closure and also an ideal one
because it creates a protected swing and
then I could look to trade this higher
here. You can see we move higher. This
time we do take out this high here and
what do we have? We have a candle 2
closure. So it is valid to look lower
here. Now we reach into this fair value
gap and what do we have? Do we have a
candle 2 closure? No. As we do not close
back inside the previous. Do we need to
wait for another candle? Do we have a
candle three closure? We do. as we close
back above the body of candle 2. So with
that then I can be looking for this move
higher. So you can see how you can
filter these swing points using candle 2
and candle 3 closures as well as which
ones have context and a point of
interest. Now how would I actually look
to frame trades in here? Well, if we go
ahead and rewind this here, what are we
looking for when we have a candle three
closure? I'm going to want to mark out
the entire candle's range. And then I
will want to see the upper half be
respected to trade it higher. So since
we are on the 4hour chart, we would go
to the 15-minute chart. And to simplify
things, I'm going to use my indicator.
So cleaning up the chart, removing all
the drawings. You can know we have that
context from the 4hour fair value gap.
We're hitting the target on this bearish
setup here, this bearish candle 2
closure. And what do we get on this new
open? We have a candle three closure. As
you can see, because we are closing over
the body of candle 2 at this reversal
point, we have a change in the state of
delivery. So, I could be looking for
entries in this next candle here. Now,
this is where I want to look for
protected swings. So, you can see we
have price reaching into a fair value
gap here, closing over these bodies
here. So, using that as my protected
swing, I could expect this low to hold.
That would allow me to take any entry in
here in the open or in the upper half of
this previous 4hour candle. put my stop
on a protected swing and look to trade
it higher. So let's see if we can get 2
R out of this or if a new continuation
would form. Anyways, let's see what
happens. So there we would get 2 R. We
come back. Let's see if we continue this
trend.
And you can see right here, what do we
have? We have a consolidation. We sweep
out the low in the consolidation. We
have a bullish bias. Now I want you to
look at this right here. Do we have a
candle 2 closure? No, we do not. So, we
would need to wait for a candle three
closure. Do we get a candle three
closure? No, we do not. So, this is an
instance where yes, I could anticipate
price to trade higher. I can anticipate
things, but my model would not align
with it as I do not have a candle 2 or a
candle 3 closure. Now, what could I wait
for? Well, once we get a closure through
the series of downcloed candles, that's
creating a new protected swing and I
have points of interest. So, I could
wait for a new swing to form if it's
going to. In this case, it does not, but
I could be waiting for a new swing to
form here to trade it higher into these
previous highs. So, this is just an
example of I want to use the candle 2
and candle 3 closures together along
with points of interest and context to
get on side with moves. I don't want to
just randomly choose swing points or
pattern trade the model. Now that you
understand the difference between a
candle 2 and a candle 3 closure, you
understand that they need context or a
point of interest and that these are the
only two formations that I look for
within my model. Let's quickly summarize
the difference between them. First off,
we always need a higher time frame key
level. As you can see in both the candle
3 and the candle 2 closure. Now with a
candle 2 closure, candle 2 will sweep
out the high of candle one or the low
and close back below it or above it in a
bullish scenario. This allows us to
anticipate a candle 3 continuation and
if candle 3 continues lower then a
candle 4 continuation as well. Now a
candle 3 closure is where we do not have
a candle 2 closure. You can see we don't
have a candle 2 closure here as it does
not close back above this previous
candle's low or candle 1's low. This
means I can't really anticipate if
candle 3 is going to run out candle 2's
low or if it's going to reverse and
trade higher. So, I'm going to let
candle 3 print and then this will allow
me to anticipate a candle 4 expansion
higher. Now, with both of these, I want
to combine it with my equilibrium video
because that is what allows me to
understand where I want to see these
higher time frame wicks form. And if you
use lower time frame change in the state
of delivery or continuation order
blocks, you essentially have my entire
model. Now, with this, I hope you found
it helpful. If you did, please consider
liking and subscribing and I'll see you
guys in the next video. Have a good one.